Guide to the Greater Houston Women's Foundation Records
University of Houston Libraries
Greater Houston Women's Foundation Records
1989-2000
1999-006
Greater Houston Women's Foundation
3.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The records of the Greater Houston Women's Foundation (GHWF) consist mainly of documents related to the organization, including financial and administrative records, membership records, newsletters, correspondence, and some oversize material such as promotional posters and placards.
Historical Note:
The Greater Houston Women's Foundation (GHWF) was established in 1990 by a group of Houston women who were concerned that only four to five percent of nationwide charitable donations were allocated to help women and girls. Consequently, the Greater Houston Women's Foundation was created to focus specifically on the needs of women and girls in Houston, and the mission of the Greater Houston Women's Foundation is to provide funding for projects and programs that benefit women and girls. Through grants, the Foundation gives back to the community seventy-five percent of the money donated.
Each year, the Greater Houston Women's Foundation awards grants to agencies and programs that are devoted to women and girls. The Grants Committee reviews proposals and makes its recommendations to the Board of Trustees, who then finalize the selection. The Foundation typically awards grants to seven to twelve agencies per year, at its annual Grants luncheon. The Foundation strives to award grants to a diversity of programs. Recent recipients include the Chinese Community Center, the Women's Home and the Women's Resource and Crisis Center in Galveston, Project Row Houses, Chinquapin School, ESCAPE Family Resource Center, the Houston READ Commission, and the San Jacinto Girl Scouts.
Education is another important component of the Greater Houston Women's Foundation The Foundation sponsors a number of educational seminars and conferences, many of which feature prominent Houston women who address issues such as career enhancement and the importance of self-confidence and self-esteem for women and girls. The main focus of the Foundation's educational efforts, is however, financial planning and money management.
The Greater Houston Women's Foundation and several institutions of higher learning in the Houston area, including the University of Houston, Texas Southern University, and Houston Community College, have worked together on research projects which examine current issues relevant to women. These studies have focused on topics such as the "glass ceiling" in the workplace, childcare and benefits, and girls and gangs. Copies of the completed research projects can be found in the Houston Public Library and its branches, and they are also distributed to elected officials. Based upon the findings of the research project, each year the Greater Houston Women's Foundation presents its Excellence awards to local businesses in recognition of their progressive policies. Recent recipients of the Excellence awards include Shell Oil Company, Mir Fox and Rodriquez, PanEnergy Corporation, and Browning-Ferris Industries.
Although no items relating to it are included in the collection, in 1992 the Greater Houston Women's Foundation, in conjunction with PBS station KUHT, developed and produced a television series entitled "Focus on Success." The Greater Houston Women's Foundation also participates in programs such as the national "Take Our Daughters to Work Day." Many prominent women have been involved in some manner with the Greater Houston Women's Foundation, including Oprah Winfrey, Nellie Connally, Elizabeth Rockwell, former Secretary of Labor Lynn Martin, former United States Ambassador to Austria Swanee Hunt, and local celebrities Jan Carson and Shara Fryer.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Greater Houston Women's Foundation
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Newsletters; Records (documents); Rosters
Topical Term:
Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Greater Houston Women's Foundation, 1999
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Linda May Papers http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=575
Scope and Contents
The records of the Greater Houston Women's Foundation (GHWF) consist mainly of documents related to the organization, including financial and administrative records, membership records, newsletters, correspondence, and some oversize material such as promotional posters and placards.
The material is arranged into eleven series: Administrative Records, Articles, Correspondence, Education, Ephemera, Financial Records, Invitations, Membership Records, Newsletters, Oversize Materials, and Studies/Research.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administrative Records, 1990-2000
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains thirteen folders, dating from 1990 to 2000. In general, the original order has been maintained, although some changes have been made to facilitate access. The folders contain minutes and memoranda of the Board of Trustees meetings and Executive Committee meetings. There were no minutes for 1992. The series also contains policies and procedures guidelines for the organization, as well as a sublease agreement. Unless they were attached to the minutes of meetings, some items, such as Treasurer's Reports have been moved to other series. The Foundation did not hold board meetings in December of any year. A number of miscellaneous financial documents were placed at the back of the original folder dated 1997, and these items have been moved and re-foldered.
  - Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committees, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grants and Grantees, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meetings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meetings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meetings, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meetings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meetings, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meetings, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Meetings, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Policies, Procedures, Plans, 1997, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sublease Agreement, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Education, 1991-1999
  This series contains ten folders, dating from 1991 to 1999. It contains materials such as flyers, brochures, and packets pertaining to educational seminars and conferences sponsored by the Greater Houston Women's Foundation. Most of the educational seminars concern financial planning and money management.
  - Moneyworks I, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Moneyworks I (in Spanish), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Moneyworks II, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Moneyworks Credit, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Moneyworks Crédito, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Moneyworks for Teens, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Moneyworks for Young Adults, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Smart Money I, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Women: Starting Out, Changing and Re-Emerging, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Education Brochures, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Studies/Research, 1992-1997
  This series contains six folders, dating from 1992 to 1997. The folders are arranged chronologically rather than alphabetically in order to show more clearly the issues of interest to the Greater Houston Women's Foundation over the years. Included in this series are the research projects and studies compiled by the Greater Houston Women's Foundation, in conjunction with such institutions as the University of Houston Graduate School of Social Work, the University of Houston College of Business Administration, Texas Southern University, and Houston Community College. Topics of the studies include the status of women and girls in Houston, corporate relationships with female-owned businesses, education and employability, and girls in gangs.
  - Greater Houston Women's Foundation Excellence Awards, Funded Research, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Promoting Partnerships: Successful Corporate Practices for Mentoring Women Business Owners, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Family Friendly Benefits: What's Happening in Houston?, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Corporate Responsibility, A Focus on Girls and Gangs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Status of Women and Girls in Greater Houston, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Gap Between Education and Employability, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, 1990-1999
  This series contains one folder of newsletters of the Greater Houston Women's Foundation, dating from 1990 to 1999. Beginning in 1992, four newsletters a year were produced. The newsletter holdings are not complete: numbers 2 and 3 of 1992 are missing; the Spring 1997 issue is missing, although it may have been made a part of the Winter 1996-1997 issue, which precedes it; the Winter 1997, Spring 1998, and the Summer and Fall 1999 issues are missing.
  - Newsletters, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Financial Records, 1990-1997
  This series contains eighteen folders, dating from 1990 to 1997. It includes records such as bank statements, financial statements, invoices, receipts, and treasurer's reports. Within the series, the sub-series are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. Most of the financial records have been left in their original order, although a few sub-series were created to facilitate access to the records.
  - Bank Statements, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bank Statements, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bank Statements, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Budget, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Deposit Account Form, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Financial Statements, 1995 and 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial Statements and Independent Auditors' Report, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial Statements and Independent Auditors' Report, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Invoices, Receipts, Expenses, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Invoices, Receipts, Expenses, January-June 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Invoices, Receipts, Expenses, July-December 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Documents, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Summary of Income and Expenses, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Tax and Appraisal Records, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1900-1998
  This series contains thirteen folders, dating from 1990 to 1998. It includes mostly thank-you notes, general correspondence to and from members of the organization, and internal memoranda. The creator had a separate folder, labeled "thank-you notes," which was arranged in roughly chronological order by year. Some items had post-it notes saying "correspo from member" or just "correspo," but all the items were in the "thank-you notes" folder. Several cards are from prominent Texas and Houston women, and the notes generally refer to luncheons, programs or fundraisers sponsored by the Greater Houston Women's Foundation.
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to GHWF, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from GHWF, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Internal Memos, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Invitations, 1991-1999
  This series contains three folders, dating from 1991 to 1999. It includes invitations to the Celebration luncheons, the Excellence awards luncheons, the Membership luncheons, and to various other luncheons, roasts and fundraisers sponsored by the Greater Houston Women's Foundation. The folder contents are arranged chronologically.
  - Annual Luncheons/Excellence Awards, 1992-1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Celebration Luncheons, 1991-1999 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Invitations, 1992-1999 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Membership Records, 1990-1994
  This series contains twenty folders, dating from 1990 to 1994. It contains records and documents pertaining to membership in the Greater Houston Women's Foundation. The materials in this series have been left in their original order. The creator organized the membership applications according to the monetary donation level. The items were then arranged alphabetically by member's name. The database membership record has been left in its original order, with some additions. Not all of the pages of the database membership record are numbered, and so page numbers and letters have been assigned to the unnumbered pages to ensure that they remain in their original order. For example, the page following 7 is 7a. In some cases, page numbers, such as 28, are missing, and there is only one page (27a) between 27 and 29. In other cases, there is a page between the numbered pages (32a is between 32 and 33), or multiple pages between numbered pages (33a and 33b are between 33 and 34). When a charter member's application was missing, the creator inserted a blank sheet with the charter member's name. The membership lists for 1992 and 1993 were arranged according to zip code, rather than alphabetically, and that arrangement has been retained. Some of the membership applications are dated and others are not. Some of these dates may pertain to a renewal of membership, rather than to an original membership. Membership records and lists cannot be photocopied.
  - Charter Affiliate Membership Applications, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Charter Associate Membership Applications, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Charter Founders Membership Applications, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Charter Investors Membership Applications, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Charter Sustainer Membership Applications, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Early Membership/Recruitment, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Founding Board, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Affiliate Membership Applications A-L, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Affiliate Membership Applications M-Z, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Associate Membership Applications, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Founders Membership Applications, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Investors Membership Applications, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sustainer Membership Applications, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Membership Applications, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Membership List, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Membership List, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Membership List, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Membership Information, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Membership Certificates and Blank Membership Applications, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Database Membership Record, 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Articles, 1900-1999
  This series contains two folders, dating from 1990 to 1999. One folder contains articles that specifically mention the Greater Houston Women's Foundation, while the other folder contains articles that concern women in general.
  - GHWF, 1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Women in General, 1994, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Ephemera
  This series contains two undated items, a pink T-shirt and a silver pin of three interlocking circles in a green felt drawstring bag. These items have been separated and placed in box 5.
  - T-Shirt, undated (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Silver Pin, undated (Box 5, Item 2)
- Oversize Materials
  This series contains fourteen oversize items, most of which are large placards and promotional materials. Only a few of the items are dated. The placards have been separated; some have been placed in oversize box 6 and three others have been placed within a folder on top of box 6.
  - Artboards for Brochures (2), undated (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Placard - Celebration Luncheon, undated (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Placard - Education, undated (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Placard - Excellence Awards Luncheon (2), undated (Box 6, Item 4)
  - Placard - Excellence Luncheon, undated (Box 6, Item 5)
  - Placard - Grants, undated (Box 6, Item 6)
  - Placard - Splashtown, 1998 (Box 6, Item 7)
  - Placard - Ticketmaster/Randalls/Channel 11, undated (Box 6, Item 8)
  - Placard - Women's Water Park Challenge, 1993 (Box 6, Item 9)
  - Placard - Endowment Campaign, 1998 (Drawer F.8, Ovs folder 6)
  - OVS Checks- United Service Association for Health Care (2), undated (Drawer F.8, Ovs folder 7)